Guide to the D'Arcy Hayman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
D'Arcy Hayman Papers,
1946-1992
Hayman, D'Arcy, 1924-
10.5 linear ft. (9 boxes and 4 flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5644461
Biographical Note
D'Arcy Hayman was for twenty years the International Arts Program director for UNESCO (1960-1980). She was also a teacher, a painter and a writer whose monographs include Embrace Me Universe and The Calculus Virgin. Born in 1924 Hayman majored in the Arts at the University of California in Los Angeles UCLA where she received her B. A. in 1949 and her M. A. in 1952. Realizing her desire to be an art instructor she went on to receive her Ph. D. and her Ed. D. from Columbia University. Hayman continued to teach art even after she joined UNESCO and in 1978 UCLA recognized her service with an Alumni Award Professional Achievement Award. During her years at UNESCO Hayman assisted the governments of the 147 Member States in promoting the arts through education international conferences television film and financial support. She worked with such luminaries as Picasso, Buckminster Fuller, Jean Cocteau, King Vidor, J. L. Borges, and Samuel Becket for multi-cultural arts highlighting special projects poster travels. She also had the opportunity to meet such illustrious personages as Eleanor Roosevelt and Ezra Pound. Among her theories is the concept that the cultural environment to which the arts contribute invaluably is as important to human survival and progress as the physical environment. After her retirement from UNESCO Hayman dedicated herself to her drawings and poetry. She has left a legacy in education the School of Arts and Architecture at UCLA has established a D'Arcy Hayman Fund and also a D'Arcy Hayman Scholarship while Santa Monica College has dedicated its Art Center which provides studio spaces for instruction in drawing and painting to Hayman s namesake.
Scope and Content
The collection comprises materials authored by D'Arcy Hayman, including letters, invitations, essays, poetry, drawings, photographs, three monographs, proofs for one monograph, journals, and three scrapbooks. The three scrapbooks are referred to as 1, 2, and 3 (1 is a photo album, while 2 and 3 contain miscellanies: essays, drawings, poems, cards, photos, newsletters, conference materials, air travel documents, clippings, post-cards, festive cup holders, and a one-act play).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Manuscripts
Series III. Scrapbooks
Series IV. Journals
Series V. Art
Series VI. Photographs
Series VII. Monographs
Subjects
Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972.; Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-1983.; Leithold, Louis.; Artists--United States--Correspondence.; Artists--United States--Diaries.; Artists--Poetry.; Drawing--20th century.; Drawing; Scrapbooks.; Photoprints.; Diaries.; Letters.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Gift of the estate of D'Arcy Hayman January 2003
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Contents: Uncollected Letters by D'Arcy Hayman, (30 letters) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters collected in Scrapbooks 2 and 3, (7 letters) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Invitations by D'Arcy Hayman, (30 invitations) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [Hayman regarded her invitations as works of art, with decorated borders, drawings, and calligraphy. Interestingly, perhaps because she regarded them as artwork, Hayman saved only her own writings to correspondents. There are no letters or invitations "to D'Arcy Hayman" in the collection. ]
- Series II. Manuscripts
  Poems are arranged in order by date (where available), so please do not disturb the sequence. The first poem in Box 2, Folder 8, was later included by its subject, Buckminster Fuller, in his book Synergistic Stew. Most of Hayman's poems, like her invitations, are decorated with illustrations and calligraphy. She uses this method of presentation - combining word and image - in her collection from 1969, Embrace Me Universe.
  - Essays and Uncollected Poetry by D'Arcy Hayman, 1947-1954, (30 poems and essays) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Uncollected Poetry by D'Arcy Hayman, 1947-1954, (30 poems and essays) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Uncollected Poetry by D'Arcy Hayman, 1947-1954, (30 poems and essays) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Uncollected Poetry by D'Arcy Hayman, 1981-1986, (30 poems and essays) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Uncollected Poetry by D'Arcy Hayman, 1981-1986, (30 poems and essays) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Uncollected Poetry by D'Arcy Hayman, 1981-1986, (30 poems and essays) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Essays and Poetry from Scrapbooks 2 and 3, (5 poems and essays) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III. Scrapbooks
  Note to 530 and 531: These are the original pages of the scrapbook in numbered order to preserve the unity of the artifact. Where possible, elements in need of preservation were removed to other parts of collection, including Box 3 and logically cross-referenced with the folders in these flat boxes. The reader will want to pay special attention to the drawings from Hayman's art classes at UCLA. By contrast, with her later abstract and primitivist work, many of these college drawings are modeled on fashion magazine art
  - Scrapbook 2, extracts, (8 drawings, poem, newsletters, newspaper clipping, one-act play) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook: 2, extracts, (20 plane ticket, brochures, newsletter, certificate, post-cards, conference schedule, autographs, news clippings, drawing) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1980, (1 t.m.) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 2 (blue binder), original pages, (10 11 x 13 thick pages on which are affixed drawings, cards, festive cup holders; some items are reproduced on acid-free paper and placed in folder inserts) (Box 530, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2 (blue binder), original pages, (18 11 x 13 thick pages on which are affixed clippings, drawings, poems, newsletters, one-act play; some items are reproduced on acid-free paper and placed in folder inserts) (Box 530, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 3 (green binder), original pages, (13 11 x 13 thick pages on which are affixed drawings, clippings, essays, poems, newsletters, postcards, conference materials, photos; some items are reproduced on acid-free paper and placed in folder inserts) (Box 531, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 3 (green binder), original pages, (16 11 x 13 thick pages on which are affixed drawings, clippings, essays, poems, newsletters, postcards, conference materials, photos, and a one-act play; some items are reproduced on acid-free paper and placed in folder inserts) (Box 531, Folder 4)
- Series IV. Journals
  - D' Arcy Hayman's Journal, 1957 January thru August, (56 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal, 1957 January thru August, (60 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - D' Arcy Hayman's Journal, 1957 thru 1958, (53 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - D' Arcy Hayman's Journal, 1957 thru 1958, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - D' Arcy Hayman's Journal, 1957 thru 1958, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Italy and Germany, (55 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Italy and Germany, (47 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Italy and Germany, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Italy and Germany, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Argentina, Bunraku, Tblishi, Sweden, Romania, (80 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Africa, (44 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Thailand, Spoleto, Teheran, Beirut, (60 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: India, Pago Pago, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Damascus, Egypt, Jordan, Turkey, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Japan, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Travels: Japan, (50 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - D'Arcy Hayman's Journal - Apollo, (60 letter-sized pages, the majority in original ink, including hand-written materials and drawings) (Box 5, Folder 31)
    [The Apollo journal (folder 31), containing Hayman's reflections on Buckminster Fuller, Religion, and Space Travel, is included here because it is continuous with the Japan journal in the original ordering. The pages in these folders have been numbered to preserve the sequence of materials as they originally appeared in the journals. Please do not disturb the sequence.]
- Series V. Art
  - Uncollected Drawings by D'Arcy Hayman, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Uncollected Drawings by D'Arcy Hayman, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Uncollected Drawings by D'Arcy Hayman, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Uncollected Drawings by D'Arcy Hayman, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Drawings from D'Arcy Hayman's Journals, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 36)
    [Pages in Folder 36-39 are numbered to preserve the unity of their original arrangement. When numbering is continuous across folders, this indicates that all the drawings in the sequence were originally bound together. Please do not disturb the order]
  - Drawings from D'Arcy Hayman's Journals, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Drawings from D'Arcy Hayman's Journals, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Drawings from D'Arcy Hayman's Journals, (30 letter-sized ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Drawings from D'Arcy Hayman's Scrapbooks, (2 ink drawings) (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Canvass drawing, (1 25 x 20 canvass) (Box 532)
- Series VI. Photographs
  - Photographs from Scrapbook 1, (22 photographs) (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Photograph 1: Buckminster Fuller, () (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Photograph 8: Eleanor Roosevelt, () (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Photographs 13-14, Ezra Pound, () (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Photograph 16: Man on the right is identified as "Maeght", () (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Photograph 23, Ezra Pound, () (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Photographs from Scrapbook 1, (22 photographs) (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Photographs from Scrapbooks 1 and 3, (22 photographs) (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Photograph 51: View of Hayman's New York Studio, () (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Scrapbook 1 (orange binder), pages 1-16, (64 acid-free reproductionsons) (Box 533, Folder 5)
    [All photos were removed from D'Arcy Hayman's Scrapbooks, including one (Scrapbook #1) devoted entirely to photos. Some personages were identifiable (see photographs above). The photocopies of the photographs have been numbered and arranged to preserve their original sequence in the scrapbooks. Do not disturb the sequence.]
- Series VII. Monographs
  - The Arts and Man (1969). Hayman wrote the Introduction to this worldwide survey of art and its functions., () (Box 8)
  - Embrace Me Universe and More (1979). By D'Arcy Hayman. Hayman's collection of her drawings and poems from the fifties and sixties. The preface is written by her friend Buckminster Fuller., () (Box 8)
  - The Calculus Virgin: An Artist's View of the Language of the Calculus (1992). Mythological interpretations of lectures on calculus, as delivered by her friend, the mathematician Louis Leithold, () (Box 8)
  - Staging Embrace Me Universe. Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (56 poems and drawings) (Box 9, Folder 44)
    [Pages in these folders have been numbered and arranged in folders to preserve the sequence of materials as they originally appeared at each stage of Hayman's planning for the book. Please do not disturb the sequence. The drawings in these folders can also be viewed in Monographs - Box 8, published version of Embrace Me Universe]
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (45 poems and drawings) (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (35 poems and drawings) (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (32 poems and drawings) (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (40 poems and drawings) (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (25 poems) (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (40 poems) (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (4 pasteboard) (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Plans and Proofs for Embrace Me Universe, (40 poems) (Box 9, Folder 52)